This is mini project 3 for xv6 in operating system concepts. Our instructor is Dr.
Luis G. Jaimes. This is a project done for his class at Florida Polytechnic University.
The contributor to this project are Nathan Cader (He wrote the report.)
Benjamin Voor (that's me. I'm making the video right now). Aiden Guenther (he took care of parts
one and two). and Khalee Johnson (who did part three). I wish we all could have written code but it
was a pretty small project actually compared to at least the first two. This project extends the XV6
operating system to correctly handle null pointer dereferences. In the original XV6, the first page
of memory is mapped and accessible which means that
address hexadecimal zero does not trap as expected.
Modern operating systems always map the first page invalid to prevent this behavior.
The objective of this project is to modify xv6 so that the null null page is always unmapped. Any
attempts to dereference the null pointer results in a trap and process termination and system
calls properly validate user pointers before accessing them. These changes are verified using
the provided test program test1-test2-test3.c, provided by said instructor Luis Jaimes
for 2025 fall semester. So to set up I'm going just show you my directory here. I'm in mini project 3
xv6_patched. So now you can see that all the files are here. All the files that you can see here.
I've already made Qemu just to have that up and running. Not running, but up. Not up, but made, so
that you don't have to load it up. You don't have to make clean and then load it and wait for that.
So if I go to the kernel make file, you can see where Aiden was uh unable to use Pearl.
So you add Pearl in and you're now able to
use Pearl. It's kind of outside the project,
but I kind of just kind of wanted to
mention it. This is one of the things he changed.
If you look here, we added test1-test2-test3 to the
one of the commands that you can
do as a user. So now this is going to
*yawn* show up when you hit "ls" and it's going to be one of the things that you can type and use.
Um, so preview make it. I've already made it. So this is going to be a very short loading sequence.
As you can see, "ls" it pops up. Uh, and I can even run it. You
can see the output here. You can
see that all three tests pass. Oh,
that's a null dereference. You can't do that. Kill the process. Test passed. Same thing.
Bad reference. Kill the process. Test pass. Test case three. Test pass. Control A X
first is kernel/exec.c. We're going to change size from zero to page size. And what
that's going to do is going to leave the first page unmapped and we're going to protect that
zone -- zones 0 to 4095 -- And if you try to access that, we're going to cause a page
fault and kill the process. Uh, and this is
going to catch null pointer bugs immediately.
In the both make files, the user make file and
kernel make file. We're going to change
the memory location to 0x1000. Um,
so 0x1000. Sorry, hang on. Sorry about that. I was saying goodbye to Thanksgiving family.
I-It's pretty late at night. So, where was
I? That's right. I'm in user make file. So,
user make file -- go to line 77. I'm going to change this section from starting
at zero to starting at the zeroth
page to starting at the first page. I hate saying that
I'm not going to say zeroth. I
hate that. I don't like saying zeroth.
We're going to go from starting at the
first page to starting at the second page
So the linker
must know where the code will run so
it can generate the correct addresses
for jumps and function calls. Since
kernel/exec.c loads user programs at 0x1000, the linker must compile them for 0x1000.
Otherwise wrong addresses will result in a crash.
So --entry=start --section-start=.text=0x1000
If I go over to proc.c here, we're going
to have, like, three things here. So I might
as well just scroll down. So "P" being proc --
-- its size is going to be two times
4096. So PAGE_SIZE, that's a constant, and it's going
to be 4096. So we're going to go double 4096
because the process's address space now spans
from zero to 0x2000, even though the first page
is unmapped. If I were to go down here to line 94,
same thing! We're going to change the
the stack pointer to double the page
size so that the stack has room to
grow downwards from the top of the
memory. And what else are we going to do
in this file? We're going to change the
instruction pointer. So at line 95, we're going to
change the instruction pointer to start at
start at zero -- to start at
page size. Why can I not select text
with the keyboard in Vim? I can only do it on my mouse. So beginning of initcode.S, change
from zero to page size. All right. So Now we're going to go into kernel/vm.C.
Here, we were starting
at zero but now we're starting at
PAGE_SIZE to map the second page rather than the
first page -- the null page -- to physical memory.
Um
same file, different line: 309. this "i=..."
initialization is going to change from zero to
page size so the "Copyuvm" function copies from the second page. This IS copyuvm. So this is the function
is we're going to change this function to copy
from the second page instead of the first page.
Um this ensures that child processes only copy
the parents memory excluding the null page.
This is the test case three. So this is going to
be the part that khalee did in fetch int method. We
don't want to extend outside of the stack into the
code of the program. So kernel just call right. So
we got a process greater than one or lesser than
4096. So this mean the first page we're going to
return negative one. We don't want that. We're
going to trap that. So this is line 22 for fetch
int and then fetch string. We're going to do
the same thing on line 39. 39. Sorry, it's 39's
a meme. Um, we're going to do the first page. Uh,
if it's there, we're going to return negative one.
So, the problem is that the addresses inside the
first four kilobytes, 4 kilobytes, 4096* 1,000,
no four times 1024 -- less than 4 kilobytes -- are never
valid user data. Real programs don't keep data
there. The OS intentionally marks it invalid. The
program fixes this by stopping bad pointers (cases a and b) before Xv6 ever dereferences them. You go
to argptr function. I think it's the same.
I think it's the same...
logic. We're just casting int i as an unsigned integer
and we're saying if it's lesser than 4096 or is
greater than equal to USERTOP we're going to
return negative one. Um so this line 70 marks the
boundary between legal user memory and the code or
kernel region. If the pointer touches that boundary
it means it points into the code segment where it
size might spill into it. The third bad pointer
starts inside valid stack memory but its length
goes past the legal range. The program fixes this
by checking blocks the entire scenario. Um PS
USERTOP is declared on
line 15 in include/param.h
as 655,360 or in hexadecimal it's
0xA0000. That's the end of the user
space. What did I do? I did not mean to do
that. I'm think I'm thinking I did control X
because I'm used to Qemu. Control A, X.
That's not that's not the correct one.
Um yeah testing cases we're going to
uncomment bounds.
Let me see the conclusion here.
This project required modifying XV6 to invalidate
the null page, update memory layout loading logic and strengthen...
that's grammatically incorrect! and
STRENGTHENING pointer validation
inside system calls. With these changes, Xv6 works like a modern OS when there's
null pointer dereferences and incorrect
syscall pointers all three test
cases from the provided test program
were successfully passed, passed, passed. Have a good day!